<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Radiology ML Tutorials</title>
<link>https://radml.wfwiggins.com/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://radml.wfwiggins.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Interactive tutorials for AI applications in radiology</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Introduction to the Command Line Interface (CLI)</title>
  <dc:creator>Walter Wiggins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://radml.wfwiggins.com/posts/intro_cli.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Before you dig into Python and get to working on your algorithms, I highly recommend that you get familiar with the <strong>command line</strong> (variably referred to as the <strong>terminal</strong> or <strong>shell</strong>, though there is a distinct difference between each of these terms). If you’ve followed our Setup Guides, then you should already be somewhat familiar with the process of running some basic commands in the terminal. Either way, we’ll start with some basic shell terminology and functionality.</p>
<hr>
<section id="terminology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="terminology">Terminology</h2>
<dl>
<dt>
Terminal
</dt>
<dd>
technically, a <strong>terminal emulator</strong>, this is the <strong>command line interface</strong> or CLI - the window to the shell
</dd>
<dt>
Shell
</dt>
<dd>
the program that runs in the terminal allowing you to interact with and manipulate files
</dd>
</dl>
<ul>
<li>each shell has its own functions, but there are many common functions and the language is mostly standardized (POSIX standard for Unix-based operating systems)</li>
<li>Commonly used shells include:
<ul>
<li><strong>sh:</strong> a basic, lightweight shell</li>
<li><strong>bash:</strong> the Bourne-again shell, the <em>most widely used</em> shell</li>
<li><strong>zsh:</strong> the Z shell, added functionality and customization geared toward increasing productivity -&gt; <strong>my preferred shell</strong></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<dl>
<dt>
Scripts
</dt>
<dd>
short programs that are written in the shell language and run from the command line
</dd>
<dt>
Process
</dt>
<dd>
a running program. Every program running on your machine right now has at least one process associated with it.
</dd>
<dt>
Dotfiles
</dt>
<dd>
files with names like <code>.bashrc</code>, <code>.zshrc</code>, or <code>.tmux.conf</code> that primarily serve as configuration files for the shell and its utilities. Most of these will live in your home folder <code>/Users/walter</code> on MacOS or <code>/home/walter</code> on Linux, both of which have the shortcut <code>~</code>.
</dd>
<dt>
Directory
</dt>
<dd>
a.k.a. folder; contains files
</dd>
<dt>
stdout
</dt>
<dd>
i.e.&nbsp;standard output; what prints to your terminal when a command or script is executed
</dd>
</dl>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="purpose-of-the-shellcli" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="purpose-of-the-shellcli">Purpose of the shell/CLI</h2>
<p>The shell is a phenomenal tool for working with and managing files that are predominantly composed of text. These include <code>*.txt</code>, <code>*.csv</code>, and <code>*.html</code> files, in addition to <em>Dotfiles</em> and files without extensions, among many other file types. The shell is also really useful for managing processes and working on remote systems, such as <em>servers</em>.</p>
<figure class="figure">
<img src="https://radml.wfwiggins.com/images/terminal-bash.png" class="center figure-img" width="100%">
<figcaption style="text-align:center; text-size=70%;" class="figure-caption">
Bash running in the Terminal app on MacOS
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><br></p>
<p>Due to the ability to work directly and efficiently with text files, the shell is a critical tool for developers and data scientists. Basically, anyone regularly writing and running code could benefit from becoming more familiar with the shell. Given its ubiquity in the tech world, there are plenty of great tutorials out there that can help introduce you to the glories of the Command Line.</p>
<figure class="figure">
<img src="https://radml.wfwiggins.com/images/iTerm-zsh.png" class="center figure-img" width="100%">
<figcaption style="text-align:center; text-size=70%;" class="figure-caption">
Zsh running in the iTerm app on MacOS
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><br></p>
<p>The tutorial I link to below is one of the more succinct introductions that should help you get started. However, it’s <em>very easy</em> to get stuck in the proverbial <strong>“Tutorial Hell”</strong>. So we won’t beat around the bush here.</p>
<p>One advantage of this tutorial is that you can run the shell code via the terminal emulator provided on the website. However, I recommend you try to get these scripts running in your own terminal.</p>
<p><strong>Note #1:</strong> As defined above, shell scripts are text files of shell code that can be run in the terminal with any output printed to the <code>stdout</code> of the shell. One way to create and run your own script is to run the following code. The structure or <em>syntax</em> of these commands is <code>command --options arg1 arg2</code>. You may not always use options or arguments (args) and some commands like <code>chmod</code> have special syntax for options.</p>
<p><strong>Note #2:</strong> in the below code, <code>#</code> precedes a “comment”, which is only intended to explain the code and is <em>not</em> executable code.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode zsh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode zsh"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">touch</span> script.sh     <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># creates a new file in the current working directory</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ls</span>                  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># list the files in the cwd, you should now see 'script.sh' among these</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chmod</span> +x script.sh  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># gives the current user execute permissions for the file</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">nano</span> script.sh      <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># open the file with the nano text editor (can use 'code' command for VS Code)</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># now you can copy and paste or transcribe the code from the tutorial into the file and save it</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bash</span> script.sh      <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># runs the script</span></span></code></pre></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://www.learnshell.org/">Learn Shell Interactive Tutorial</a>: Proceed to the linked page and complete each exercise under “Learn the Basics”.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>After you complete this tutorial, check back for the next Command Line post, where we’ll download some data for an intro to Machine Learning in Radiology and use shell functions &amp; scripts to rename and move files into a more convenient directory structure before we move on to implement our first algorithm.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://radml.wfwiggins.com/posts/intro_cli.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Installing Python with uv</title>
  <dc:creator>Walter Wiggins</dc:creator>
  <link>https://radml.wfwiggins.com/posts/install-python.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In this post, we’ll cover a new-ish command line tool called <code>uv</code> that serves as both a Python <strong>package manager</strong> and project management tool. We’ll utilize this to install Python and set up an example coding project.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://radml.wfwiggins.com/images/uv-docs.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">uv documentation page: <a href="https://docs.astral.sh/uv/"></a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="python" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="python">Python</h2>
<p>Python is an interpreted programming language, sometimes referred to as a scripting language. It has been referred to as the <em>lingua franca</em> of AI and ML, so this is the language I use for all my interactive sessions and tutorials. The base Python installation comes with a number of packages for basic operations one might want to do when coding in Python. One of those packages is <code>pip</code> which is a package manager. This allows you to install other packages built for specific tasks. For example, you may want to install <code>numpy</code> so you can do numerical computing with arrays, or <code>pandas</code> so you can work with tabular data, or <code>pytorch</code> so you can do deep learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="uv-for-package-management" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="uv-for-package-management"><code>uv</code> for Package Management</h2>
<p><code>uv</code> is a faster package manager that also comes with other features to assist with project management. One such feature is <strong>virtual environment</strong> management. Having a virtual environment or “env” allows you to install packages specific to a project. Different projects (or tutorials) may require different versions of the same packages, or even a different version of Python itself. Installing those packages in an env helps you avoid conflicts between packages/versions in your base Python installation.</p>
</section>
<section id="version-control" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="version-control">Version Control</h2>
<p>Another project management feature of <code>uv</code> is a tool called <code>git</code> for version control of coding projects. You can learn more about it at the link below. For now, you can think of it as a way to keep track of changes you make in your code, so that you can more easily revert to an earlier version if you make a change that breaks something. <code>git</code> also helps with managing collaborative development projects.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Missing Semester: git (Version Control)
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>To learn more about <code>git</code>, check out this lecture from MIT’s <em>The Missing Semester of your CS Education</em> course: <a href="https://missing.csail.mit.edu/2020/version-control/">git (Version Control)</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="installation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="installation">Installation</h2>
<p>Open up your terminal application, then copy and paste the following code into the terminal window to install <code>uv</code> on your system.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">wget</span> <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-qO-</span> https://astral.sh/uv/install.sh <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">|</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sh</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Alternatively, if you’ve installed Homebrew on your system, you can copy and paste the following command into your terminal window to install <code>uv</code>.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">brew</span> install uv</span></code></pre></div>
<p>It is wise to periodically update the libraries you have installed on your system. If you used the first command to install <code>uv</code>, then you may update the library with the following command.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">uv</span> self update</span></code></pre></div>
<p>Otherwise, you may update <code>uv</code> with <code>pip</code> after you’ve installed Python.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Important
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>You must install Python before you run the following command.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pip</span> install <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--upgrade</span> uv</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="installing-python-with-uv" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="installing-python-with-uv">Installing Python with <code>uv</code></h2>
<p>Now that <code>uv</code> is installed, you are able to install a base version of Python to use regardless of whether you’ve setup a virtual environment for a given project.</p>
<p>If you have a recent model of Mac, then Python is likely already installed on your system. Run the following command in your terminal to see if Python is already installed and, if so, which version.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb5-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">python</span> <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--version</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>You can use <code>uv</code> to manage previously installed Python versions. Run the following command if you’d like to use and update the existing version of Python.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb6-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">uv</span> python install <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--reinstall</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>If you do not yet have Python installed, run the following command to install it with <code>uv</code>.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb7" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode sh code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb7-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">uv</span> python install</span></code></pre></div>
<p>With that, you should have a working base installation of Python, so any time you create a virtual environment with <code>uv</code>, it will include that base version by default unless you specify a version of Python to use.</p>
<p>In the next post, we’ll setup a virtual environment and install <strong>Pytorch</strong> – one of the leading libraries for deep learning.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://radml.wfwiggins.com/posts/install-python.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
